
<p>Men beloved, we told you erewhile how our Saviour Christ was on this day born in true human nature of the holy Virgin Mary. Nevertheless, we now desire, for the honour of this day, to stir your minds by ghostly teaching for your happiness, by the grace of God. There were certain heretics beguiled by the devil, so that they said that Christ the Son of God was not eternally dwelling with the Holy Father, but there was a certain time (period) before He was born; but the holy Gospel hath full oft surpassed the understanding of such heretics. The Jews asked Christ who He was; then answered He them thus:
  <hi xml:lang="la" rend="italics" ref="John 8:25"><!-- biblical text as outside reference source, how to code? -->
    Ego sum principium qui et loquor uobis</hi>: <hi rend="quoted">'I who speak unto you am the beginning.'</hi>
    Now have ye heard how Jesus spake of Himself, that He is the Originator and Beginning of all things, together with His Heavenly Father and with the Holy Ghost. The Father is the Beginning, and the Son is the Beginning, and the Holy Ghost is the Beginning; they are not three Beginnings, but they all three are one Beginning, and One Almighty God, ever unbegun and unended. But the man is mad who wishes to have anything before a beginning; because the Holy Trinity is the Beginning and the One Creator of all creatures, and there never was nor now exists anything that the One Worker hath not created. If any heretic or frenzied man seek to enquire further and go beyond the beginning with foolish presumption, he is like unto a man who reareth a high ladder, and climbeth by the steps of the ladder until he be come to the end, and then, desiring to climb yet higher, he climbeth without the steps until that, having no standing-place, he falleth with so much the worse a fall as he further clomb.
</p>
<p>There are three things on this earth: one is transitory, which hath both beginning and end; such are beasts and all soulless things which began when God created them, and afterward come to an end and turn to nothing....
</p>
